Aliciam
The College of Saint Rose Archives
Aliciam Collection
1845-1957
Aliciam
The College of Saint Rose Archives
0.4 Linear feet (1 box)
This collection includes materials by and about Alice Meynell. Most notably, however, is the collection of famous authors’ signatures and correspondence.
Moran, John Joseph, Sister
Conditions Governing Access note
There are no restrictions to this collection.
Biographical/Historical note
Aliciam began as the honorary, literary society of Saint Rose in December 1930. The members named the club, Aliciam, as a tribute to an English woman poet, essayist, and critic. This woman was Alice Meynell, one of the first popular woman poets. Mr. Wilfrid Meynell, her husband, became the first member of Aliciam.
The club was for those majoring or minoring in English, and an average of over 85 was required to join. There were monthly meetings in which the members read and discussed outstanding poetry. Each member had to present one long critical paper within the year. In the early 1950's there was a slight change to include more genres of literature, rather than concentrating completely on poetry. They ceased writing papers and, instead, showed literary films and put on plays. The group collected signatures of famous authors and poets.
The first officers were Monica Branigan-president, Helen Welsh-vice president, Nan Maginn-secretary, and Helen Wheeler-treasurer. Sister John Joseph Moran started Aliciam, and administered it until she retired. Sister Jeanne Pierre Mittnight took charge and changed the name to The Literary Society in 1966. In 1977 she dissolved it because there was no longer an interest in departmental clubs.
Arrangement note
This collection is divided into the following series:
Materials about Alice Meynell and Family, 1946-1948
Materials by Alice Meynell, 1902-1931
Correspondence, 1931-1951
Famous Authors’ Letters and Correspondence, 1845-1957
Mittnight, Jeanne Pierre, Sister
- Materials about Alice Meynell and Family, 1946-1948
  - Thesis: "Contemporary criticism, personal and literary, of Alice Meynell." Aileem R. Mahar. Boston University Graduate School., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Materials by Alice Meynell, 1902-1931
  - Letter: From Alice Meynell to?, 04/02/1902? (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Essays of Today and Yesterday, signed by Wilfrid Meynell, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Selected Poems of Alice Meynell, signed by Wilfrid Meynell, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Augustan Books of Modern Poetry, signed by Wilfrid Meynell, 1931? (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - I am the Way, undated; 5.0 Item(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1931-1951
  - Letter: To Sister John Joseph Moran from Wilfrid Meynell, 1/8/1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter: To Aliciam member Monica Branigan from Wilfrid Meynell, 5/11/1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter: To Sister John Joseph Moran from Wilfrid Meynell, 8/11/1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter: To Sister John Joseph Moran from Viola Dallyn, 2/21/1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Famous Authors’ Letters and Correspondence, 1845-1957
  - Joseph Campbell, 1930 and 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Thomas Campbell, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - G.K. Chestertown, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James Fenimore Cooper, 06/16/1845 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Robert Frost, 1934 and 1944 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Florence Hardy, 3/11/1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Jay William Hudson, 5/18/1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Vachel Lindsay, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Jacques and Raissa Maritain, 12/13/1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alfred Noyes, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - E.G. Robinson, 2/28/1933 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carl Sandburg, 10/20/1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - unknown, 10/28/1865 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - unknown, 04/09/1889 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - unknown, 11/27/1900? (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - unknown, 2/10/1936 (Box 1, Folder 27)